<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Tiago Ventura</title>
    <link>/authors/tiago-ventura/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Tiago Ventura</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2018 Tiago Ventura</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 15 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/authors/tiago-ventura/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Will I get COVID-19? Partisanship, Social Media Frames, and Perceptions of Health Risk in Brazil</title>
      <link>/publication/will_i_get_covid/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/will_i_get_covid/</guid>
      <description>We report results of a COVID-19 social media framing experiment with positive and negative partisan messages from high-level politicians. Descriptive results show that pro-government and opposition partisans report very different expectations of health and job risks. Job and health policy have become wedge issues that elicit partisan responses. Experimental treatment shows that responses are sensitive to negative frames (i.e. blame avoidance) and positive frames (i.e. cross-the-aisle)</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Effect of Streaming Chat on Perceptions of Debates.</title>
      <link>/publication/streaming_chat/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/streaming_chat/</guid>
      <description>We investigate how streaming chatboxes may shape perceptions of political events. We conducted a field experiment during the September 2019 Democratic Primary Debate where subjects were assigned to view the debate with or without streaming chatboxes. Subjects were encouraged to view the debate on the ABC homepage (with no chatbox), on FiveThirtyEight.com (expert chat) or on Facebook (social chat). Our experimental findings indicate that Democratic subjects assigned to the Facebook chat condition reported lower affect towards Democrats and a worse viewing experience.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Winning! Adjudication and Dialogue in Social Media</title>
      <link>/publication/adjudication/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Dec 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/adjudication/</guid>
      <description>This article introduces the concept of adjudication to define the act of granting or denying ownership of an outcome to individuals or groups in social media. We extend existing models of political dialogue to explain differences between winners and losers when elections are adjudicated.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Polarization, News Sharing, and Gatekeeping: A study of the Bolsonaro Election</title>
      <link>/publication/bolsonaro/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Oct 2019 15:35:10 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/bolsonaro/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Going Local to Win the Nation: Political Boosting in Mayoral Politics.</title>
      <link>/publication/boosting/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Oct 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/boosting/</guid>
      <description>In this paper, I show that parties in Brazil boost their national performance earning more votes on House elections in districts where their members control the local office.  I discuss how higher access to pork controlled by House members and information gains from local incumbency explain the effects. Using a Bayesian LASSO algorithm to address data sparsity in RD designs, I further show the existence of pro-large party bias.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>News by popular demand: Ideology, Reputation, and Issue Attention in Social Media News Sharing</title>
      <link>/publication/news_by_popular_demand/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 May 2019 13:51:56 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/news_by_popular_demand/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>More Participation, Greater Responsiveness? National Public Policy Conferences and the Quality of Democracy in Brazil</title>
      <link>/publication/responsiveness/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Sep 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/responsiveness/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Workers&#39; Party in the Chamber of Deputies: the evolution of the socioeconomic and territorial bases (1994–2014)</title>
      <link>/publication/pt_electoral_bases/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Jul 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/pt_electoral_bases/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Democracy and participation. Democratic innovations and participatory routee in Brazil</title>
      <link>/publication/my-paper-name/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Sep 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/my-paper-name/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>