<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Social Media on Tiago Ventura</title>
    <link>http://tiagoventura.rbind.io/tags/social-media/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Social Media on Tiago Ventura</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2018 Tiago Ventura</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 14 Mar 2021 15:35:10 -0400</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="http://tiagoventura.rbind.io/tags/social-media/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Partisan Cues and Perceived Risks: The effect of partisan social media frames during the Covid-19 crisis in Mexico</title>
      <link>http://tiagoventura.rbind.io/publication/covid_mexico/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 14 Mar 2021 15:35:10 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://tiagoventura.rbind.io/publication/covid_mexico/</guid>
      <description>Abstract We present the results of a survey experiment designed to evaluate the effects of social media exposure on perceptions of personal health and job risks during the COVID-19 pandemic in Mexico. Our framing experiment treats respondents to positive and negative partisan messages from high-level politicians. Descriptive findings show divergent evaluations of how the government is addressing the crisis by supporters of the government and opposition parties. Results show that respondents are sensitive to negative frames regardless of the political color of the messenger.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Connective Effervescence and Streaming Chat During Political Debates</title>
      <link>http://tiagoventura.rbind.io/publication/bringing_back_audience/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Jan 2021 15:35:10 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://tiagoventura.rbind.io/publication/bringing_back_audience/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Trustful Voters, Trustworthy Politicians: A Survey Experiment on the Influence of Social Mediain Politics</title>
      <link>http://tiagoventura.rbind.io/publication_wp/trust/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 29 Nov 2020 15:35:10 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://tiagoventura.rbind.io/publication_wp/trust/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Trustful Voters, Trustworthy Politicians: A Survey Experiment on the Influence of Social Mediain Politics</title>
      <link>http://tiagoventura.rbind.io/talk/trust/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 29 Nov 2020 15:35:10 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://tiagoventura.rbind.io/talk/trust/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Will I Get Covid? Partisanship, Social Media Frames, and Perceptions of Health Risk in Brazil</title>
      <link>http://tiagoventura.rbind.io/publication/will_i_get_covid/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26 Oct 2020 15:35:10 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://tiagoventura.rbind.io/publication/will_i_get_covid/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Polarization, News Sharing, and Gatekeeping: A study of the Bolsonaro Election</title>
      <link>http://tiagoventura.rbind.io/publication/bolsonaro/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 Oct 2020 15:35:10 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://tiagoventura.rbind.io/publication/bolsonaro/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Effect of Streaming Chat on Perceptions of Debates</title>
      <link>http://tiagoventura.rbind.io/publication_wp/streaming_chat/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 May 2020 15:35:10 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://tiagoventura.rbind.io/publication_wp/streaming_chat/</guid>
      <description>Abstract We investigate how streaming chatboxes may shape perceptions of political events. We conducted a field experiment during the September 2019 Democratic Primary Debate where subjects were assigned to view the debate with or without streaming chatboxes. Subjects were encouraged to view the debate on the ABC homepage (with no chatbox), on FiveThirtyEight.com (expert chat) or on Facebook (social chat). Our experimental findings indicate that Democratic subjects assigned to the Facebook chat condition reported lower affect towards Democrats and a worse viewing experience.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Effect of Streaming Chat on Perceptions of Debates</title>
      <link>http://tiagoventura.rbind.io/talk/streaming_chat/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 May 2020 15:35:10 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://tiagoventura.rbind.io/talk/streaming_chat/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>News by popular demand: Ideology, Reputation, and Issue Attention in Social Media News Sharing</title>
      <link>http://tiagoventura.rbind.io/publication_wp/news_by_popular_demand/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 May 2019 13:51:56 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://tiagoventura.rbind.io/publication_wp/news_by_popular_demand/</guid>
      <description>Abstract In this article we describe a method to estimate the determinants of news sharing in social media. We model news sharing as a function of three behavioral parameters that describe the (i) ideological (cognitive) congruence between the users and the news published by a media organization; the (ii) reputation of the media organization; and the (iii) user&amp;rsquo;s attention to issues. The statistical model takes observational social network data as input and extracts all three parameters of interest.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>News by popular demand: Ideology, Reputation, and Issue Attention in Social Media News Sharing</title>
      <link>http://tiagoventura.rbind.io/talk/news_by_popular_demand/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 May 2019 13:51:56 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://tiagoventura.rbind.io/talk/news_by_popular_demand/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
