<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Ernesto Calvo on Tiago Ventura</title>
    <link>http://tiagoventura.rbind.io/authors/ernesto-calvo/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Ernesto Calvo on Tiago Ventura</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2018 Tiago Ventura</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 29 Nov 2020 15:35:10 -0400</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="http://tiagoventura.rbind.io/authors/ernesto-calvo/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Trustful Voters, Trustworthy Politicians: A Survey Experiment on the Influence of Social Mediain Politics</title>
      <link>http://tiagoventura.rbind.io/publication_wp/trust/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 29 Nov 2020 15:35:10 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://tiagoventura.rbind.io/publication_wp/trust/</guid>
      <description>Abstract Recent increases in uncivil dialogue, political polarization, and fake news in social media raise questions about the relationship between negative online messages and the decline in political trust. We implement a trust game in a survey experiment with 4,800 respondents in Brazil and Mexico. Our design models the effect of social media on trust and trustworthiness. Survey respondents alternate as agents (politicians) and principals (voters), with rewards contingent on their preferred “candidate” winning the election.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Partisan Cues and Perceived Risks: The effect of partisan social media frames during the Covid-19 crisis in Mexico</title>
      <link>http://tiagoventura.rbind.io/publication_wp/covid_mexico/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 15 Nov 2020 15:35:10 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://tiagoventura.rbind.io/publication_wp/covid_mexico/</guid>
      <description>Abstract We present the results of a survey experiment designed to evaluate the effects of social media exposure on perceptions of personal health and job risks during the COVID-19 pandemic in Mexico. Our framing experiment treats respondents to positive and negative partisan messages from high-level politicians. Descriptive findings show divergent evaluations of how the government is addressing the crisis by supporters of the government and opposition parties. Results show that respondents are sensitive to negative frames regardless of the political color of the messenger.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Will I Get Covid? Partisanship, Social Media Frames, and Perceptions of Health Risk in Brazil</title>
      <link>http://tiagoventura.rbind.io/publication/will_i_get_covid/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26 Oct 2020 15:35:10 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://tiagoventura.rbind.io/publication/will_i_get_covid/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Polarization, News Sharing, and Gatekeeping: A study of the Bolsonaro Election</title>
      <link>http://tiagoventura.rbind.io/publication/bolsonaro/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 Oct 2020 15:35:10 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://tiagoventura.rbind.io/publication/bolsonaro/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Winning! Adjudication and Dialogue in Social Media</title>
      <link>http://tiagoventura.rbind.io/publication_wp/adjudication/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Dec 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://tiagoventura.rbind.io/publication_wp/adjudication/</guid>
      <description>This article introduces the concept of adjudication to define the act of granting or denying ownership of an outcome to individuals or groups in social media. We extend existing models of political dialogue to explain differences between winners and losers when elections are adjudicated.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>News by popular demand: Ideology, Reputation, and Issue Attention in Social Media News Sharing</title>
      <link>http://tiagoventura.rbind.io/publication_wp/news_by_popular_demand/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 May 2019 13:51:56 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://tiagoventura.rbind.io/publication_wp/news_by_popular_demand/</guid>
      <description>Abstract In this article we describe a method to estimate the determinants of news sharing in social media. We model news sharing as a function of three behavioral parameters that describe the (i) ideological (cognitive) congruence between the users and the news published by a media organization; the (ii) reputation of the media organization; and the (iii) user&amp;rsquo;s attention to issues. The statistical model takes observational social network data as input and extracts all three parameters of interest.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
